howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show listeners have asked us to
provide pointers some of the resources
we talked about on the show we now have
links to books and articles referenced
in recent podcasts that are available on
our website
we also offer full transcripts go to Jim
rut show.com that's Jim ruts show com
this is another one of our extra Kovach
19 episodes the sound quality won't be
as good as some of our regular episodes
but the ideas will be as rich in as deep
maybe more so today's guest is Nora
Bateson Nora is an award-winning
filmmaker writer and educator as well as
president of the International Bateson
Institute her work asks the question how
we can improve our perception of the
complexity we live within so we may
improve our interaction with the world
what a huge question and how timely well
welcome Nora good it's out with you
again nice to be here Jim thank you for
inviting me oh it's always great to talk
that you have such a fresh mom it's
really fresh mind you think about things
in ways that other people don't and
always so kovat 19 complexity our
interactions with the world you know
time sense-making what are you thinking
well one thing that i'm i'm we were just
pop talking about time before we got
started and I think the time question is
really there's something interesting
happening there because we're all locked
in our houses and for most of us right
now the the scheduling routines and the
clocking of our days the calendaring of
our time is really different than it
used to be there's not a lot of going
and coming happening right now for most
of us some people are still
the essential workers are still clocking
in and clocking out but but we're in a
strange parallel moment and at first I
didn't you know really notice it but
after a week or so maybe maybe it was
two weeks I just started to notice that
this constant din of conversation with
family members and friends and so on and
so forth about comings and goings that
all of that conversation was actually
gone and in that there was a kind of a
deeper level of shifting relationship to
time and one of the other aspects of
this is that in them in the meanwhile
spring is coming so there's another time
happening demarcate it by I don't know
where you are but in Sweden the the
early flowers are starting to come and
we've had a little snow flurry today but
it was just one of those you know last
flirtations of winter but it's really
spring and so there's this sort of deep
time and and just very different
relationship to time in general so
that's an interesting thing and and part
of that of course I think is also
mortality I turned 52 today it's my
birthday thank you I'm a full deck of
cards now no one can say you shy of a
deck anymore
because I got the whole deck now but
this is for me in my life one of the
first times when I started to really
think about you know I'm not I'm not
over into the high-risk zone but I'm not
in the low-risk zone and but that's
another sort of question of time
interesting yes so you have personal
time which is your own clock right
all as we get older I'm quite a bit
older than you we hear the ticking of
the clock a little louder every year
click click click but then we also as a
you know I'd really like your insight
into the nature of our local time and
the rhythms that we have and now don't
have its think about how much we're
conversations are about our we're about
our trivial comes and coming and goings
that's now gone may and probably there
are wins and losses from that one that
did provide a rhythm to the day but on
the other hand it was fairly banal to
tell you the truth maybe we're having
some deeper conversations I know we are
around here at the at the rut farm and
you know I am in the you asked where I
was I'm up in the mountains of western
Virginia and we're in a glorious early
spring right now or I'm looking out the
window at a giant maple tree out along
on one of our fence lines that's just
kind of getting those those yellowish
leaves before the leaves go full and our
gardens are full of 20 different kinds
of daffodils and bloodroot and that
sounds beautiful
oh yeah this is a place that's just
sublime one of things we have talked
about more than we normally would have
which is how you know amongst all the
bad things that Cove at 19 at least it
didn't come in the middle of the winter
right that would have been our sole
breaker if this had happened then you
know mid-december or something we all we
could think of is worse and worse
weather at least we have better weather
now and getting better every day but
anyway we you know this this different
texture of time is quite interesting and
maybe this is a good time to pivot to
one of the main things I want to talk to
you about is we're all going through a
unique experience in world history
something like this has never happened
before in fact one of my previous guests
so it was Jessica flack said that one of
the most interesting things about this
as never has the human race operated
cooperatively at the scale you know
essentially billions of people are all
playing to a theme in variation on the
same tune in more or less real-time and
then on another the other level the fine
grain of our local time is different
we're nowhere near
is distracted by all the activity that
we spend our life in so we have time to
think some of us you know what's the
other side of this what are the
opportunities and the risks of the other
side of koban 19 because this too will
pass right we're least here in the
United States we're probably the numbers
I saw from University of Washington
yesterday we're probably a week from the
peak of the total active number of
infections and all then start going down
and there'll be all kinds of
difficulties in managing the back side
of the curve but at least the the
infectious peak we're almost to the top
and so there will be another side the
Sun will come out and what happens what
are the what are the interesting things
on the other side of this from your
perspective one thing that I think is
important to think about is this
question of what's important and that's
been just put front and center what is
essential and it started you know sort
of around questions of who are the
essential workers but also when you go
to the store now or you're thinking
about what you're gonna actually go out
into vector world to to purchase there's
this question of what's essential and do
I really need this and if I didn't get
to build a relationship with this person
before is it essential to make peace and
what started to come into focus for me
is that that this experience right now
is can be seen as a kind of interruption
and that that there were a certain sort
of patterning that we were living in for
better or worse it seems like it had a
lot of worse side to it quite a bit of
destruction to the ecology and
exploitation of people and so on and so
forth nevertheless time was
Bing and we were moving within it within
this all the systems kind of had their
own sort of clocking happening and then
there's this interruption and we're all
home or both you know there's a lot of
people who are in hospitals and that
question of what's essential comes in
and I what I started to sort of reflect
upon is this question of what which
thing is the interruption because in
fact I started to notice that it didn't
take very long before I was speaking to
my children in different ways about
making things last thinking about
putting vegetables in the garden doing
things and thinking about life in
another kind of time another texture as
you put it and the in fact that seems to
be much more of a continuation of
something that I would imagine my
ancestors might have had access to that
texture of time where I I have been in
this kind of hectic kind of metallic
time of the modern world the digital
metallic time of of the last several
decades
so where switch parts the interruption
and the the metaphor I keep thinking of
is that that that sort of the modernity
has offered us the opportunity to just
go to the faucet and get water but this
kind of time feels much more like the
deep aquifer and it's the so I'm just
kind of wondering which piece of this is
the interruption and which piece is the
continuation lovely point of view lovely
and you mentioned the you know the
different ways we deal with things they
give you a personal example here at the
house
you know we've been buying supplies once
every two weeks we go to town and do the
pickup with our masks and our gloves and
all this stuff and so we got a little
milk and a little bit of it aged out was
getting a little sour you know normally
we probably would have poured it out but
no instead we just poured it into our
yogurt maker right and and as you said
much like particularly my mother's
family who were subsistence peasants
essentially who lived off the land for
as far as I know back to the last ice
age right that was a very interestingly
different way than those of us who could
just assume we'd run up the road and buy
a gallon of milk if the milk a little
sour and which ones the interruption
damn good question
what do you think will be on the other
side of this how many people you think
will make take this opportunity to
reconnect with perhaps earlier or or
different patterns well this is kind of
where I was going with this is because I
I find that working with complexity one
of the things that that we do all the
time Jim is we're constantly trying to
help people work out how to think about
causation without getting caught in
linearity right and when you look
backwards it's it's a little bit more I
guess it depends on how you're looking
what sort of perception what sort of
lens you have but if there is that the
ability to perceive in sort of nonlinear
ways you can start to see that this is
not really about the virus it's about
the viruses arrival into a multi
systemic fragility that has been cooking
for quite a while and so on and so forth
so there's where's the causality it's
kind of all over the place now what
happens when you apply that to the dream
or the dreaming the fantasy the the
fiction of what's going to happen next
and if you start to think about how you
think about the future with that same
non-linearity
I think that becomes a really
interesting question because so often
you get futuristic visions that are
frankly pretty flat and they they don't
have all that juicy stuff of the details
of what kind of decisions and habits you
and I and so many other people are
actually remaking right now oh and I
don't think we even know what those
details will look like I just I you know
what what if this beginnings of things
last actually took root what would that
do to the economy what would that do to
technology what would that do to to just
an entire way of life and pace of life
if there weren't built-in obsolescence
very good questions and you know some of
us in the game be world have used the
word liminal to talk about those times
when you're entering into a zone where
your former experience is less
informative about the future than usual
and this strikes me as certainly one of
those times right as you said I have a
sense that there's a great opportunity
here for change for the better but the
details I'm not sure I see them yet and
probably won't until we start to live
them I think this is a great opportunity
for people to live different live their
way into someplace better yeah and I
think it's a that it's a great
opportunity to pay attention to the
details because the details will in fact
be what we the pathways we start to live
into and so it makes a huge difference
and and just thinking also about being
stuck in our various dwellings some
people are stuck alone and some people
are stuck with other people but in
either case there are moments of doing
that that are not easy the people that
you love are a lot easier
live in peace with when you are not with
them all day every day a little flare-up
here yesterday and I go oh dear but
that's life okay we have to learn to
deal and learning to communicate and
recognizing in this type of moment that
there's a need to be kinder but we can't
just close the door and shut it down and
be angry or make melodrama or you know
that that's just useless because you
have to actually you know if there lack
of a better metaphor if you on the
floor you gotta sit in it like that's
how it is right now so and then for
those people that are all by themselves
there's also that question of
relationship to the self relationship to
other people how that communication is
happening what that reach out looks like
what the reach-in looks like and so you
know if the world is made of
relationships in interdependency and
those relationships start to change and
the communication within those
relationships start to change we're
going to see changes and how the second
and third order of those changes start
to manifest I think we have absolutely
no idea but I'm very curious and and I'm
I'm so hoping that we're not going into
police state ugliness I'm so hoping that
this is a possibility for there to be
more integrity and carefulness in all
the relationships in our lives from the
relationship to our own bodies and and
that recognition that your health is not
your own health right you go into into
town to go to the shops and you think
wow you know somebody's there thinking
well I'm not afraid of this virus it's
not gonna kill me but but that person
you know it's like look it isn't really
about you right it's it's about your
hell
is is my health is my mother's health is
you know this is a multi-generational
multi communal health question your
health is not your own and all those
relationships that perception is
shifting so maybe it's gonna be possible
to have more integrity more perception
of how how intertwined the well-being of
one and all is and and I don't mean that
in the kind of hallmark systems-thinking
way you know there's this kind of
version of systems thinking that can get
very meanness and I'm not I'm not down
with that but but I am wanting to push
and and and explore this idea of what
does it look like to actually approach
the multitude of relationality
in our lives with a higher degree of
attention and integrity that would be
really really good
if this tragedy which it is can take us
to that better place but as you point
out there are other pathways which would
not be so good I mean we also
unfortunately have to keep our political
diligence on to make sure that
powers-that-be don't use this you know
legitimate application of some top-down
action in a kind of warfighting mode to
you know switch states permanently into
a surveillance state or a police state
so there's also some dangers and we have
to be cognizant of both the
opportunities and the dangers and and
act accordingly
I was wondering what kind of political
platforms will come after this just
noticing I mean what's happening with
crime right now right what's happening
with education like all the usual hot
topics are in a state of transformation
and it's it's just there's so much
that's in that liminal liquid form right
now it's all very blurry
yeah the basics you know sort of how we
organize production in our society it
strikes me this this ought to be ought
to be if people have ears to hear not
all will that the relentless drive
towards efficiency of the engine of
short-term money on money return and
it's clearly taking us to a point of
danger I mean this literally danger
we'd been better prepared in terms of
robustness and resilience this would
have been way less of a problem than it
was and could also at least from my
perspective my game be perspective it's
an argument for subsidiarity I eat the
idea that local communities need to be
more self-sufficient self-governing need
to understand what the explicit ties
they have to other regions are and
frankly work to keep those under control
you know for instance suppose
Westchester County in New York where the
first flare-up occurred New Rochelle had
organ and I have been organizing itself
bottoms up in its relationship with the
wider world and had only a certain
amount of links out of its County when
this flare-up happened have been easy to
snip all those links and say alright
Westchester Counties shut down for four
weeks but we have lots of stockpiles of
medical equipment and food and and such
so we'll get through this just fine
instead the relentless attempt to
squeeze the last nickel out of
everything we're a t-shirt that used to
be made in South Carolina and in a
factory providing a living for a
thousand people was shipped off to
Bangladesh because at the end of the day
even including transport and everything
else the t-shirts five cents cheaper
right that's that's the kind of thinking
that drives the current I call it insane
money on money return engine and maybe
just maybe the fact that this is life
and death for actual people who really
experience the downside cost of not
investing in
local not investing in robustness not
investing and resilience will open
people's ears just to thinking a little
bit differently about how we organize
our society well it's that question you
use the word efficiency and you know
when you're working on a machine you
optimize for efficiency when you're
working with living systems like
societies or families or forests or you
you cannot optimize for efficiency you
have to optimize for interdependent
health otherwise you lose and so if
there's a real shift that's possible
there and it might be a side effect of a
lot of people a lot of businesses going
bankrupt supply chains that could get
broken things that just cannot reboot
because they've lost too much to catch
up again if this you know will we again
see the days of mass quantities of as
you say you know cheaply produced goods
way too cheaply produced goods but
didn't reflect the cost of human life or
the natural resources is there a chance
that we may have crossed into a new era
of recognizing when we don't need
something first of all but second of all
that you that thing that you want to buy
costs a lot more because that's what it
actually costs without just all the
money going to the CEOs I I don't know
what will happen with this it's like
this thing about the toilet paper you
know it could have been anything that
had gotten into people's ideas of things
that they desperately needed as
essential it could have been the fact
that it was toilet paper it could have
been in in Sweden it was yeast and flour
you just you can't buy yeast anywhere
so apparently everybody's home baking
bread yeah we're doing that and
fortunately we laid in 200 pounds of
flour as part of our long term emergency
hoard and my wife has her a nice
sourdough culture so even though we also
have some yeast even when we run out of
yeast we have our self-replicating
sourdough but it could have been
anything and thinking about you know
when I plant my garden I noticed you
know I didn't plant any wheat in my
garden actually there's no grains at all
in my garden and so what does that what
kind of what kind of shift in in
thinking about food is that so there's
just shifts everywhere from how we talk
to the kids to how we are with our
partners to how we think about the
elders to how we you know honor and
respect the health care workers to
questions I think big questions right
now about how science is responding to
this and how to respond to a complex
problem how how how clean of politics is
scientific research and development how
is it possible to get it outside of the
economic momentum and the various clouds
of greed and fame and those things that
have come in to the culture so how do we
begin to even come into these ways in
different in different times there
because it's it's a different time now
so what are these things six weeks ago
they were on a kind of indelible
uninterruptible impossible to stop train
and suddenly the tracks are shattered
for the moment and I think this is the
the biggest question of all after this
shock when we think about complex
adaptive social biological systems we
often see too
different tendencies when a shock is
given to the system once called
homeostasis which is the tendency for
things to knit back together the way
they were I think thinking of yourself
you have a cold or you bruise on your
elbow you know in two weeks you're fine
again is if nothing had happened
on the other hand if someone you know
chops off your leg it's never gonna grow
back you know I'll say in a farming
accident so you have homeostasis and
then you have hysteresis the tendency
for the shock to push us into a new
trajectory and that's what I am just
obsessing about clearly in the rhetoric
and for specially for politicians there
just seems to be a gigantic libido at
least in the public discourse to return
to normal return to where we are and yet
in the world of social change activists
folks like yourself and a lot of other
people we both know we're all seeing
this is perhaps an opportunity for
hysteresis to move the world in a new
direction what do you think about that
you know the force for return versus the
forces for a new trajectory I mean I
think they're both in play
absolutely so it's some things will go
back and some things will change and the
things that change will change the way
things go back and the things that go
back will change the way things change
you know there's it's a kind of
inseparable process yeah I mean it some
there is that's why I was asking that
question about continuing right what is
continuing and what are the essentials
that need to continue and I think for
some people that essential is the is
wall street for other people that
essential is just intergenerational food
on the table how do we feed the babies
how do we take care of each other how do
we take care of our communities but then
you think okay so I'd like to put in a
garden I need to get a new hose and I
can't get the hose because the hose has
to be brought in from the other side of
the world so there's there's so many
different and this is what I was saying
sort of about the the non-linearity of
future speculation they interact with
each other you know our expectations our
experience and then this is where the
hysteresis comes in the actual effect of
this shock it's back to some things we
were talking about earlier in this
bubble at a time that will cause many of
us to have thought in maybe perhaps more
deeply and at least more originally than
we had in a long time and then those new
thoughts will also be part of this
unfolding in a nonlinear way exactly and
it will materialize in the strangest
most unexpected details we know from
complexity that we can't predict the
details but hey speculate anyway any
ideas that you know that have come to
struck your mind
now let's you know that's not what let's
say these are mr. dominoes the level
predictions but any just thoughts on
what we might see on the other side well
I think we're gonna see some shifting in
relationships to education for sure we
might see some shifting in relationship
to screens because this technology is
but what if when we get free of this it
seems like there could be a kind of
saturation point for the addiction that
was brewing you know I like all of that
nagging at the children to get off the
screens and now I'm nagging at them to
get on the screens and do their homework
and and I'm on the screens all day long
I can't wait to get off and get outside
or do something that's a little more
analog my nervous system feels different
than it did six weeks ago how is yours
Oh nervous system I don't know probably
unchanged I'm a pretty resilient kind of
person I will also say that for the last
year I've been doing most of my work
quote/unquote on zoom' and so this
changes and all that big for me I mean
yes I still miss my you know lunch and
get-togethers with
friends around town and things of that
ilk but you know I don't notice a
gigantic difference in my nervous system
itself now one level up the cognitive
state the contents the cognitive
contents definitely are different and
again for the reasons we talked about
there's more time away from the
trivialities for the brain to the
cognitive state consciousness to wander
a field and and poke its fingers into
ideas that it never had time for before
so I would make that distinction nervous
system feels normal cognitive state
feels like it has explored places it
normally had yeah I can relate that I
did a lot of traveling and public
speaking so I I'm so happy to be out of
airports in hotel rooms I just can't
even tell you that is one of my
predictions by the way the business
travel will not return to anything like
the level it had before because because
so many of us have now I mean I've been
doing this for years but for a lot of
people this is the first time they have
seen that you know damn Skype is pretty
good or zoom is pretty good and you know
flying from you know New York California
to have one one-hour meeting how many
times have I done that my life Jesus
takes three days out of my life and
costs $2,000 when I could have had you
know 30 hour-long skypes in that time
frame which one is better for getting
work done first but also consider the
environment while you know computation
is not cost free in terms of the
environment I can wear on piya then a
one-hour skypes carbon footprint is a
thousand times less than flying my wide
body across the country
staying in annex you know overheated
hotel eating restaurant food and riding
around in taxis for three days so you
know I think this is one of these
hysteresis things that will be gigantic
and then I get for this other good yeah
I got a puppy this week and that's
that's my way of saying I agree with
that hysteresis point obviously I'm not
traveling for a while and you'll enjoy
it
you'll be a better person for it
probably know there will be some there
will be some losses probably frankly to
the other people who would normally
interact interact with you face-to-face
who they will get they will lose some of
that because there is iam we are you
know I always tell young business people
are confused by a business meeting for
instance I'd say just imagine the
participants in the business meeting as
Apes with clothes right and then
suddenly it'll make a lot more sense and
it's amazing they'll go damn Jim I can
now understand there's this meeting and
we are Apes with clothes and Apes do
like grooming right being with each
other physically so there is something
lost from going from business meetings
to zooms but you know my hopefully big
takeaway here is once the plague lifts
which it will is to recommit myself to
local face to face which is cheap carbon
neutral
you know just use the old feet right and
you know invest in building those strong
ape-like links with our physical
neighbors rather than feeling the need
to dash around the countryside and do so
and the local goods as well so I guess
one of the other things I'm becoming
very aware of is like I was saying about
the hose for the garden there's a lot
that's being transported across the
world that you know it's just
unnecessary so I think that's that's
part of it redundancy local redundancy
this is I think gonna get picked up and
I I wonder what really what we will be
asking of political leaders in the
future I just I think that the whole
like you were talking about game a but
the whole that whole existing system got
so out of control it was really at the
level of you know kind of Marie
Antoinette absurdity just copious
extravagance and paying far too much
attention to things that were
essential and I just hope that that if
there's change that it's toward paying
attention to be essential and for me
that essential is really the those
interrelationships and community family
relationship to their natural world you
know health health health is ooh is a
very precious asset I love it I'm gonna
wrap it up there I think this will be a
wonderful exploration of our minds and
our possibilities going forward like
that really thank you Nora for for being
on the show thank you Jim it's always
such a pleasure so whenever you want to
talk just give me a call I will take you
up on that production services and audio
editing by Jared Jane's consulting music
by Tom Muller at modern space music com
[Music]